I will always remember
سوف أتذكّر دائما
the first time I met the girl in the blue uniform.
أول مرّة قابلت فيها الفتاة بالبدلة الزرقاء.
I was eight at the time,
كنت في الثامنة من عمري حينها،
living in the village with my grandmother,
أعيش في القرية مع جدتي،
who was raising me and other children.
حيث تربّيت ومعي مجموعة من الأطفال الآخرين.
Famine had hit my country of Zimbabwe,
عانت بلادي زمبابواي من المجاعة،
and we just didn't have enough to eat.
ولم يكن لدينا ما يكفي من الأكل.
We were hungry.
كنا جائعين.
And that's when the girl in the blue uniform
وعندها أتت الفتاة ذات البدلة الزرقاء
came to my village with the United Nations
إلى قريتنا مع الأمم المتحدة
to feed the children.
لإطعام الأطفال.
As she handed me my porridge,
وعندما أعطتني العصيدة،
I asked her why she was there,
سألتها لماذا هي هنا،
and without hesitation, she said,
ومن دون تردد، قالت لي،
"As Africans, we must uplift all the people of Africa."
" كإفريقيون يجب علينا النهوض بكل سكّان افريقيا "
I had absolutely no idea what she meant.
لم يكن أدنى فكرة عن ما قصدته بكلامها هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But her words stuck with me.
ولكن بقيت كلماتها عالقة في ذهني.
Two years later,
بعد مرور عامين،
famine hit my country for the second time.
شهدت بلادي مجاعة للمرة الثانية.
My grandmother had no choice but to send me to the city
لم يكن لجدتي خيار سوى إرسالي إلى المدينة
to live with an aunt I had never met before.
للعيش مع خالة لم أقابلها قط في حياتي.
So at the age of 10,
لذا في سن 10 سنوات،
I found myself in school for the very first time.
وجدت نفسي في المدرسة لأول مرة.
And there, at the city school,
وهناك، في حي المدرسة،
I would experience what it was to be unequal.
عشت تجربة ما معنى أن تتعرض للامساواة.
You see, in the village,
كما تعرفون، في القرية،
we were all equal.
كنا جميعا ننعم بالمساواة.
But in the eyes and the minds of the other kids,
ولكن في أعين وعقول الأطفال الآخرين،
I was not their equal.
لم أكن مساوية لهم.
I couldn't speak English,
لم أكن أستطيع تكلم الإنجليزية،
and I was way behind in terms of reading and writing.
وفي ما يخص القراءة والكتابة كنت سيئة جدا.
But this feeling of inequality would get even more complex.
وكان الشعور بالامساواة يزاد تعقيدا مع الوقت.
Every school holiday
في كل عطلة مدرسية
spent back in the village with my grandmother
أقضيها في القرية مع جدتي
made me consciously aware
جعلتني أدرك
of the inequalities this incredible opportunity
التفاوتات التي خلقتها
had created within my own family.
هذه الفرصة المدهشة داخل عائلتنا.
Suddenly, I had much more than the rest of my village.
فجأة، أصبحت أتلقى أكثر من متساكني القرية.
And in their eyes, I was no longer their equal.
وفي نظرهم لم أعد مساوية لهم.
I felt guilty.
شعرت بالذنب.
But I thought about the girl in the blue uniform,
ولكن فكرت في الفتاة ذات البدلة الزرقاء،
and I remember thinking,
وأتفكر أنني قلت في نفسي،
"That's who I want to be --
هذاهو ما أريد أن أصبح عليه --
someone like her,
شخصا مثلها،
someone who uplifts other people."
شخصا ينقذ الآخرين. "
This childhood experience led me to the United Nations,
هذه التجربة الطفولية هي التي مكنتني من الإنضمام إلى الأمم المتحدة،
and to my current role with UN Women,
ودوري الحالي ضمن نساء الأمم المتحدة،
where we are addressing one of the greatest inequalities
حيث نتعامل مع أسوأ حالات اللامساواة
that affects more than half of the world's population --
التي يعاني منها أكثر من نصف سكان العالم --
women and girls.
النساء والفتيات.
Today, I want to share with you
اليوم، أريد أن أشارككم
a simple idea that seeks to uplift all of us together.
فكرة بسيطة ستمككنا من النهوض ببعضنا البعض
Eight months ago,
خلال 8 أشهر الماضية،
under the visionary leadership of Phumzile Mlambo-Ngcuka,
تحت إشراف فومزيلل ملامبو نجوكا،
head of UN Women,
رئيسة الأمم المتحدة للمرأة،
we launched a groundbreaking initiative
قمنا بإطلاق مبادرة مميزة
called HeForShe,
تدعى هو من أجلها هي "HeForShe"،
inviting men and boys from around the world
والتي من خلالها دعونا الرجال والفتيان
to stand in solidarity with each other and with women,
للتضامن في ما بينهم ومع النساء،
to create a shared vision for gender equality.
لخلق نظرة مشتركة حول المساواة بين الجنسين.
This is an invitation for those who believe in equality
هذه دعوة لأولائك الذين يُؤمنون بالمساواة
for women and men,
بالنسبة للرجل والمرأة،
and those who don't yet know that they believe.
وأولائك الذين ليسوا على علم بإيمانهم.
The initiative is based on a simple idea:
ترتكز هذه المبادرة حول فكرة بسيطة:
that what we share is much more powerful
بأن النقاط المشتركة هي أقوى
than what divides us.
من النقاط التي تُفرقنا.
We all feel the same things.
كلنا نشعر بنفس الشيء.
We all want the same things,
كلنا نريد نفس الشيء،
even when those things sometimes remain unspoken.
حتى تلك الأشياء التي لا يتم الحديث عنها.
HeForShe is about uplifting all of us,
مبادرة" هو من أجلها هي" هي حول النهوض ببعضنا البعض
women and men together.
النساء والرجال معا.
It's moving us towards an inflection point for gender equality.
والتي تحثنا على تحقيق المساواة بين الجنسين.
Imagine a blank page
تخيل ورقة بيضاء
with one horizontal line splitting it in half.
مع خط أفقي في الوسط.
Now imagine that women are represented here,
والآن تخيلوا أن النساء يتم تقديمهم هنا،
and men are represented here.
والرجال هنا.
In our current population,
بالنسبة لسكاننا الحاليين،
HeForShe is about moving the 3.2 billion men,
شملت مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" إلى حد الآن 3.2 بليون رجلا
one man at a time,
في كل مرة يعبر رجل
across that line,
ذلك الخط،
so that ultimately, men can stand alongside women
اذن في الأخير يقف الرجال في صف النساء
and be on the right side of history,
وسوف يكون لها مكانة تاريخية هامّة،
making gender equality a reality in the 21st century.
بتحقيق العدالة بين الجنسين خلال القرن 21.
However, engaging men in the movement would prove quite controversial.
ولكن مع ذلك إدراج الرجال خلال هذه الحركة سيكون محل نقاش.
Why invite men? They are the problem.
لماذا استدعاء الرجال؟ فهم المشكلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, men don't care, we were told.
ولكن، الرجال لا يهمهم ذلك، هذا ما تم إخبارنا به.
But something incredible happened when we launched HeForShe.
ولكن حدث شيء مدهش عند إطلاق مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي".
In just three days, more than 100,000 men
خلال 3 أيام فقط، انخرط أكثر من 100000
had signed up and committed to be agents of change for equality.
رجل والتزموا بالمساهمة في تحقيق التغيير من أجل المساواة.
Within that first week, at least one man in every single country in the world
في ظرف أسبوع، على الأقل رجل من كل بلد حول العالم
stood up to be counted,
إنضمّ إلى المبادرة ليتم احتسابه،
and within that same week,
وفي نفس ذلك الأسبوع،
HeForShe created more than 1.2 billion conversations on social media.
خلقت مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" 1.2 بليون مناقشة على المواقع الإجتماعية.
And that's when the emails started pouring in,
وعندها تهاطلت علينا الرسائل الإلكترونية،
sometimes as many as a thousand a day.
في بعض الأحيان ألف رسالة في اليوم.
We heard from a man out of Zimbabwe,
سمعنا من رجل في زمبابوي،
who, after hearing about HeForShe,
بعد سماعه لهذه المبادرة،
created a "husband school."
قام ببناء "مدرسة الزوج"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He literally went around his village,
فلقد تجول في جميع أرجاء قريته حرفيا،
hand-picking all of the men that were abusive to their partners,
ليختار جميع الرجال الذين يقومون بتعنيف زوجاتهم،
and committed to turn them into better husbands and fathers.
ليلتزم بتغييرهم إلى أزواج وأباء صالحين.
In Pune, India, a youth advocate organized an innovative bicycle rally,
في مدينة بوني بالهند قام شاب بتنظيم مسيرة للدراجات،
mobilizing 700 cyclists
محفزا 700 راكبا للدراجات
to share the HeForShe messages within their own community.
لإيصال رسائل مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" لمجتمعاتهم.
In another impact story,
وفي قصة أخرى،
a man sent a very personal note
أرسل رجل رسالة شخصية جدا
of something that had happened in his own community.
لشيء ما حدث بمجتمعه.
He wrote,
كتب،
"Dear Madam,
" سيدتي،
I have lived all of my life
لقد عشت حياتي كلّها
next door to a man who continuously beats up his wife.
بجانب رجل يقوم بتعنيف زوجته بصفة مستمرة.
Two weeks ago,
وفي الأسبوعين الماضيين،
I was listening to my radio,
كنت أستمع إلى المذياع،
and your voice came on,
وسمعت صوتك،
and you spoke about something called the HeForShe,
ولقد كنت تتحدثين عن شيء يُدعى "هو من أجلها هي"،
and the need for men to play their role.
والحاجة الملحة للرجال للقيام بدورهم.
Within a few hours, I heard the woman cry again next door,
وفي غضون عدة ساعات، سمعت المرأة تبكي مرة أخرى،
but for the first time,
ولكن لأول مرّة،
I didn't just sit there.
لم أجلس هناك بلا حراك،
I felt compelled to do something,
لقد شعرت بضرورة القيام بشيء
so I went over and I confronted the husband.
لذلك توجهت إلى هناك وواجهت زوجها.
Madam, it has been two weeks,
سيدتي، الآن مضى أسبوعان،
and the woman has not cried since.
ولم أسمع صوت بكاء المرأة منذ ذلك الحين.
Thank you for giving me a voice."
شكرا لمنحي هذه الفرصة. "
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Personal impact stories such as these
إن مثل هذه القصص الشخصية
show that we are tapping into something within men,
دليل على أنه كان لنا تأثير على الرجال،
but getting to a world where women and men are equal
ولكن تحقيق المساواة بين الرجل والمرأة في العالم
is not just a matter of bringing men to the cause.
لن يكون بمجرد نسب هذه القضية للرجال.
We want concrete, systematic, structural change that can equalize
نريد تغييرا ملموسا ومنهجيا وهيكلي يُمكّن من تحقيق المساواة
the political, economic and social realities for women and men.
على مستوى الواقع السياسي والإقتصادي و الإجتماعي بين الرجل والمرأة.
We are asking men to make concrete actions,
نحن نطلب من الرجال القيام بأعمال ملموسة،
calling them to intervene at a personal level,
ودعوتهم للتدخل على المستوى الشخصي،
to change their behavior.
لتغيير سلوكهم.
We are calling upon governments, businesses, universities,
نحن ندعو الحكومات والشركات والجامعات،
to change their policies.
لتغيير سياساتهم.
We want male leaders to become role models
نريد من القادة الرجال أن يكونوا نموذجا
and change agents within their own institutions.
وأن يتم تغيير سلوك العاملين داخل شركاتهم.
Already, a number of prominent men and leaders have stepped up
حاليّا، بدأت مجموعة من الرجال البارزين في العمل بذلك
and made some concrete HeForShe commitments.
وقاموا بالتزامات ملموسة لمبادرة "هو من أجلها هي".
In a few early success stories,
خلال عدد من القصص الناجحة،
a leading French hospitality company, Accor,
التزمت شركة صحية فرنسية بارزة،
has committed to eliminate the pay gap
بالقضاء على فجوة الأجور
for all of its 180,000 employees by 2020.
لكل موظفيها 180000 بحلول عام 2020.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The government of Sweden,
التزمت حكومة السويد
under its current feminist government,
في ظل الحكومة النسائية الحالية
has committed to close both the employment and the pay gap
بسدّ الفجوة لكل من التشغيل والأجور
for all of its citizens within the current electoral term.
لجميع المواطنين ضمن الدورة الإنتخابية الحالية.
In Japan, the University of Nagoya
باليابان، بجامعة ناغويا تم البدء ببناء
is building, as part of their HeForShe commitments,
مركز، كجزء من الإلتزامات بمبادرة "هو من أجلها هي"
what will become one of Japan's leading gender-research centers.
والتي ستكون أحد مراكز البحوث الرائدة بين الجنسين.
Now, eight months later,
والآن، بعد ثمانية أشهر،
a movement is building.
بدأت حركة في الظهور.
We are seeing men sign up from every single walk of life,
بدأ الرجال في الإنخراط من مختلف المستويات،
and from every single corner in the world,
ومختلف أنحاء العالم،
from the United Nations' own Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon
بدء من الأمين العام للأمم المتحدة بان كي مون
to the Secretary-Generals of NATO and the EU Council,
وصولا إلى الأمين العام لكل من الناتو ومجلس الإتحاد الأروبي
from the prime minister of Bhutan
بدء من رئيس وزراء بوتان
to the president of Sierra Leone.
وصولا إلى رئيس سيراليون.
In Europe alone, all the male EU Commissioners
في أوروبا فقط، جميع المفوضين الرجال للإتحاد الاروبي
and the members of Parliament of the Swedish and Iceland governments
وأعضاء البرلمان للحكومات السويدية والإسلندية
have signed up to be HeForShe.
قاموا بالإنخراط بمبادرة "هو من أجلها هي".
In fact, one in 20 men in Iceland has joined the movement.
في الحقيقة، رجل من أصل 20 بإسلندا التحق بالحركة.
The rallying call of our passionate goodwill ambassador, Emma Watson,
أثارت الدعوات المكثفة لسفيرتنا المتحمّسة إيما واتسون،
has garnered more than five billion media impressions,
حوالي 5 بليون انطباعا من قبل وسائل الإعلام،
mobilizing hundreds and thousands of students around the world
وهو ما أدى تحريك المئات والألاف من الطلاب حول العالم
to create more than a hundred HeForShe student associations.
لإنشاء أكثر من 100 جمعية "هو من أجلها هي".
Now this is the beginning of the vision that HeForShe has
هذه فقط البداية لهذه المبادرة "هو من أجلها هي"
for the world that we want to see.
التي نريد رؤيتها حول العالم.
Einstein once said,
قال انشتاين مرّة،
"A human being is part of the whole ...
" الإنسان هو جزء من كلّ...
but he experiences himself,
ولكنه خاض التجربة مع نفسه،
his thoughts and feelings,
ومع أفكاره ومشاعره،
as something separate from the rest ...
كشيء منفصل عن البقية...
This delusion is a kind of prison for us ...
هذا الوهم هو نوع من السجن لنا...
Our task must be to free ourselves from this prison
ومهمتنا هي أن نتحرر من هذا السجن
by widening our circle of compassion."
بتعميم الرحمة على أوسع نطاق. "
If women and men are part of a greater whole,
إذا كان الرجل والمرأة جزء من الكل،
as Einstein suggests,
كما اقترح انشتاين،
it is my hope that HeForShe can help free us to realize
أملي أن تساعد مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" في تحريرنا
that it is not our gender that defines us,
لنُدرك أن النوع لا يحدد هويتنا،
but ultimately, our shared humanity.
ولكن في نهاية المطاف، إنسانيتنا المشتركة.
HeForShe is tapping into women's and men's dreams,
مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" هي كشف عن أحلام كل من الرجل والمرأة،
the dreams that we have for ourselves,
أحلامنا،
and the dreams that we have for our families, our children,
والأحلام التي لدينا من أجل عائلاتنا وأطفالنا،
friends, communities.
وأصدقاءنا ومجتمعاتنا.
So that's what it is about.
إذن هذا ماهو عليه الحال.
HeForShe is about uplifting all of us together.
مبادرة "هو من أجلها هي" هي من أجل النهوض معا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)